[
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 1,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section A: AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>THE BLOOD OF A STRANGER — DELE CHARLEY </strong></p><p> </p><p>How does the love for wealth and power influence the actions of the characters in the play?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Some of the characters demonstrate love for money. ie. greed and ambition, throughout the play. Whitehead. the White man and Stranger, Maligu, the King's adviser and Soko the Village Shrine Priest, are three of the characters that demonstrate this vice. Their sole objective is to get rich. Whitehead comes to Mando land intending to plunder the wealth of the people and carry away their diamonds, under the pretext of tobacco farming.</p><p>Greed sets in when Maligu and Soko begin to lose trust in one another and plan to get rid of each other for the greater advantage of the diamond wealth. The three want Kondo, the son of the king of Mando nd and head of the warriors, out of the way for em to succeed in their plan. Kindo recognizes it when he tells Maligu to \"pray for greed and ambition not to destroy\" him. Whitehead also wants Parker, an African who acts as his secretary and as assistant interpreter, and Soko killed as they do not <br>\nexactly fit into his plan beyond using them to achieve his aim. When Maligu stands the chance to save Whitehead from death on his hands, he betrays him and simply thanks him for the diamond wealth that now apparently belongs to him alone. </p><p>It is clear that some of the major characters of the play do not show concern for the good of all in Mando land but for themselves alone. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 2,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section A: AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p><strong>BLOOD OF A STRANGER — DELE CHARLEY</strong></p><p> </p><p>Assess Santigi's reign as King of Mando land. </p>",
        "answer": "<p>Santigi reigns in a time of peace, the people of Mando land having come out of previous wars with neighbouring tribes. Assisted by Maligu his 'wise counsellor' and Soko, the priest, and his son who is Chief of the Warriors, he appears to be heading towards a quiet and peaceful death in his dotage (old age). </p><p>However, Santigi's kingdom is suddenly ruffled by the news of Soko's contrived divination of a white stranger appeared in the land. Aided and abetted by Maligu and Soko, the whiteman, symbolically, called. Mr. Whitehead, who has sent his messenger/secretary (interpreter...,), Mr. Parker (for short) before him, appears, much against the custom of the people and does not pay his respects to the king upon arrival, which is also against custom. Kindo the king's son, points this out, but his appeal is ignored by the king who rigidly insists on things being done according to custom. </p><p>Whitehead's arrival in Mando land bodes no good for the people of Mando land under Santigi's reign. In complicity with Maligu and Soko, he deceives the King (urged on by Soko and Maligu) that he brings prosperity to Mando land through the introduction of tobacco farming, when his real interest is the land's diamond. Kindo, who suspects his real motive, which is exploiting the diamond resource of the land, is never listened to by his father, the king. Thus, Santigi's reign is characterised by the violation of custom after custom; for instance, the custom which forbids the people to smoke tobacco (Maligu, Soko and the king indulge in this pastime). Later, the people become addicted to tobacco, alcohol and hard drugs and, as reported by Kindo, the men and women engage in sexual orgies, as societal norms and restrictions are abandoned \" in the name of happiness under the very eyes of Santigi\". A normally self-sustaining farming people lose the will to work hard and embrace laziness, rather. </p><p>Things do not improve, even at this stage, as Whitehead and his accomplices, Maligu and Soko, single out Kindo, the King's son, as the main obstacle to pursuing their greed for money and wealth.. They hatch a plot which receives the king's support. To atone for the arrival of the stranger within, there should be a sacrifice involving \" the blood of a stranger born in another place\". Soko interprets this as being the blood of a virgin. Wara, Kindo's woman, is chosen. However, such is the distrust between the accomplices that Soko spares Wara's life and on the day of the sacrifice, Kindo kills Parker, Whitehead's secretary, who then becomes the sacrificial lamb. Santigi sits on his throne unaware of the demands of his own custom and acquiesces to Wara being sacrificed instead. It takes Kindo to expose the grand deception and the killing of Whitehead to stop the descent into the depravity that has engulfed the people. Ironically, Kindo's banishment is sanctioned by his own father, King Santigi, according to custom.</p><p>Here, therefore, is a kind who, though old and insistent on tradition, has no high moral integrity to show in his violation of custom for money. Instead of protecting his people from outside negative influence, he superintends a corrupt and effete society which is unlikely to improve under an equally corrupt Maligu, if he should die and Kindo is unable to return from banishment.</p><p>When it emerges that it is Parker who has been sacrificed instead, Whitehead calls for the enforcement of the tradition which prescribes death for anybody who kills in peace time. Whitehead in turn dies on Kindo's sword, accidentally. </p><p> </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 3,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section A: AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>HARVEST OF CORRUPTION - FRANK OGODO OGBECHE</strong></p><p> </p><p>Comment on the proceedings of the Wasa High Court of Justice </p>",
        "answer": "<p>Investigations into the activities of Chief Haladu Ade-Amaka are already in progress when Ogeyi goes to the police on account of her friend Aloho. Her story helps the police to wrap up their investigations and prefer charges against Chief and five others, including Ochuole, at Wasa High Court of Justice presided over by Judge. </p><p>It appears that only a fraction of the Minister's sins against the state and some people is known. According to Judge, \"For all the atrocities you must have perpetrated in this country under the cover of Minister, which have not been detected, I say nothing.\" Chief then faces four counts of embezzlement, involving 1.2 billion naira and 5.8 million naira (two counts); dealing in cocaine and corrupting a public officer.</p><p>Prosecution Counsel clearly outlines the role of the police in their investigation and what makes each accused person culpable. Inspector Inaku's evidence is clear and concise. What triggers police investigation is set down as \"Miss Ogeyi Ogar and the Jacassan Flash of 21st June, 1997\". Following the newspaper report, the inspector goes to the Ministry and bribes Mr. Ayo to get access to official documents. By the inspector's own admission, Mr. Ayo does not ask for a bribe; rather, the Clerical Officer \"promised to cooperate after I enticed him with the sum of two thousand naira\". This show of zeal is wrong. The law seems to be that both the giver and the receiver of a bribe are criminals. One would expect; then, that the court reprimand or even sentence inspector I naku once Mr. Ayo goes in for five years. </p><p>In her evidence, Ogeyi clearly tells Aloho's story and firmly incriminates Chief. Her reason for going to the police is consistent with her love for her late friend; failing to persuade Aloha not to abort the pregnancy, she \"was moved to go to the police to relate the story\". However, Chief lies on oath, alleging that the \"cocaine had been put there to incriminated\" him. In the end, the court does not believe him and his breaking down avails him nothing. Of the two, Ogeyi is found credible by the court.</p><p>Both counsels do their work to the best of their abilities. Prosecution Counsel notes and draws attention to Defence Counsel's \"cleverly weaving the evidence of the prosecution to confuse this honourable court\". He draws the court's attention to the relevant flaws in the case of the defence and leaves the rest to the judge and the jury. The judge sums up succinctly and his guiding of the jury is balanced. </p><p>On the whole, the proceedings go well and the verdict arising from the evidence appears to be satisfactory. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 4,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section A: AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>HARVEST OF CORRUPTION - FRANK OGODO OGBECHE</strong></p><p> </p><p>Consider Aloho as a foil to Ogeyi.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Aloho and Ogeyi are friends from their university Jays. They are both pretty, slim and of average hieight. While Aloho is dark-skinned, Ogeyi is fair. They are both born-again Christians. </p><p>Years after their graduation, Ogeyi secures a job, with the ABC Company as a receptionist, while Aloho is still searching for employment. Ogeyi, though not that well off, is very benevolent. She does not only accommodate and feed Aloho, she encourages her to be patient and not lose faith in God. </p><p>When Aloha comes homes with the promise of a bogus' job by a 'notorious friend', Ogeyi counsels caution, but in Aloho's frustration and desperation, She flouts Ogeyi's advice and accepts the job of a protocol officer in the Ministry of External Relations. </p><p>Ogeyi does not give up in her preachings; she tries to dissuade Aloho, but her words fall on a deaf ear as the glitter of the good life eggs Aloho on. Aloho soon finds herself in police custody for trafficking drugs</p><p>As soon as she is cleverly acquitted and discharged through the corrupt string-pulling of Chief Ade-Amaka, Aloha discovers that she is pregnant. She attempts to abort the pregnancy but fails due to her nightmarish dreams, Dr. Chukwuma the gynecologist's evasive delay tactics and Ogeyi's fervent dissuasion. </p><p>In her cornered and remorseful situation, she finally returns to her family, but later dies in childbirth, though the baby survives. </p><p>Ogeyi launches into action to seek justice for her friend's death. She testifies boldly in court against Chief Ade-Amaka, helping to bring him to his deserved \"harvest\". </p><p>Thus, one can conclude that Aloho is a foil to Ogeyi, as her actions accentuate the wonderful qualities that Ogeyi is endowed with. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 5,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON - AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>A RAISIN IN THE SUN - LORRAINE HANSBERRY</strong></p><p> </p><p>What is the significance of Karl Linder's visit to the Youngers?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Karl Lindner is a whitemen. He visits the Younger home twice on the same day. The purpose of his visits is to persuade the Youngers not to move into the house that Mama has bought in Clybourne Park for the family. These visits are significant for understanding some aspects of the world of the play. </p><p>The day Lindner goes to see the Youngers they are preparing to move. \"The Man\" meets Beneatha, Ruth and Walter. Mama is out. Lindner's mission is simple: The Clybourne Park Improvement Association has sent him to let \" you people\" know that they do not want the Younger family in the neighbourhood, for the whitemen there come from \"a common background\" to which the Youngers are unwanted aliens. He assures Walter that the \" overwhelming majority of our people out there feel that people get along better, take more of a common interest in the life of the community when they share a common background.\" For that reason, the whitemen want \"to buy the house from you at a financial gain to your family.\" The mission fails as Walter orders Lindner out of the house. As he goes out perplexed, Lindner leaves his card. </p><p>Lindner's second visit is at the invitation of Walter. Ostensibly, Walter wants to seal the deal of the sale of the house. But this does not happen. Walter has been inspired by his mother's fighting spirit to reject the offer of Lindner with finality. Lindner, of course, does not understand fully as he departs. </p><p>These visits are significant for understanding the Negro experience and the black-white relationship in America. Bobo's intervening report of the loss of the family money that Walter has handed over to Willy Harris for the liquor business gives the family a philosophical outlook. Walter learns from here and takes the bold decision. It will be incompatible with the family's pride to agree to sell the house since \"ain't nobody in my family never let anybody pay iern no money that was a way of telling us we wasn't fit to walk the earth.\" This is how succinctly Mama explains what Lindner seeks to do. Because \"we ain't never that poor \", the family must stick to its purpose and move into the new house. Mama is larger than life, as they say, and her stand establishes her as such. The speed with which waiter picks the import of the philosophy is astonishing. This is a proud family and must hang on hope with tenacity. It is this that makes Walter decline Lindner's offer with finality and for which Mama commends Walter as having `finally come into his manhood'. </p><p>Though Lindner protests that his visit and the Clybourne Park residents' resistance to the Younger family's occupation of the property has no racial implications or racist undertones, that is not what the visit shows. The whiteman wishes to have little to do with the Negro as a neighbour. It is Lindner's conviction and that of the white community in CLybourne Park that our Negro families are happier when they live in their own communities\". </p><p>Lindner's visits, therefore, reveal the reality of whie rejection of Negroes as neighbours and the determination of the Negroes to improve the circumstances of their life at all cost. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 6,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>A RAISIN IN THE SUN - LORRAINE HANSBERRY</strong></p><p> </p><p>Trace the transformation of Walter \"Into his manhood' in the play?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Walter, as a man, should have been head of the Younger family. Yet, it is Mama who has been at the helm of affairs from the outset. Not satisfied with his station in life, Walter is preoccupied with his dream of making it big through the investment of money that is not his own. He dreams constantly of becoming a self-made man with the backing of his wife, while complaining that no one understands him. Several times he has proved a disappointment to Mama. </p><p>Uncaring about what goes on around him, Walter gets a good opportunity of showing himself as the worthy man his mother expects his mother expects him to be when his wife decides to have an abortion. Typically, he is not even aware of his wife's condition <br>\nuntil Mama tells him. Mama urges him to take the bull by the horns and speak firmly to his wife and talk her out of her decision. He falters in this and, bitterly disappointed, Mama calls him a \"a disgrace to your father's memory\". </p><p>When George Murchison calls to take Beneatha out, Walter is inexplicably rude to the young man. He will not leave them alone despite Ruth's many attempts to have him behave civilly. George aptly describes him as \" all whacked up with bitterness\". On his part, Walter goes on and on about his vision and his being little understood. Unable to see the wisdom in Mama's buying the house with the insurance money, Walter becomes bitter. He is rude at home and even absents himself from work. Hurt because his mother will not approve his liquor business intentions, he gets another chance to prove worthy as head of family \"like you supposed to be\", when Mama entrusts the remainder of the insurance money to him with specific instructions. Walter speedily goes and hands all of it over to Willy Harris who takes off with the money. </p><p>The final opportunity to become the man he should be comes when he rejects Lindner's offer to buy Mama's new home. Bobo's report that Willy has bolted with the money shows that the family has no more of the precious insurance money left. This makes the prospects of moving into 406 Clybourne Street in the white neighbourhood of Clybourne Park particularly bleak and precarious. </p><p>The man in Walter emerges, however, and he invites Lindner over. Under a show of accepting the whiteman's offer to buy out the family, and contrary to the family's fears, he rejects the offer. He tells Lindner. \"We have decided to move into our house ... don't want your money\". All this while, Mama has been showing her approval, \"as though she were in church with her head nodding the amen yes\". </p><p>Thus, from a spineless dreamer and loafer, Walter transforms into a responsible head of the sixth generation Younger family. Henceforth, things look secure in his hands. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 7,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON - AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>SHE STOOPS TO CONQUER - OLIVER GOLDSMITH</strong></p><p> </p><p>Examine the importance of the Jewels in the play</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The jewels in the play refers to the box of jewels that is constance Neville's inheritance left in the care of Mrs. Hardcastle, her aunt.</p><p>Mrs. Hardcastle does not want to release the jewels to the rightful owner, Constance. She intends to keep such inheritance in her family. Therefore, she covers up this intention by forcing Constance to marry Tony, her mischievous son.</p><p>Constance is wise enough to play along with Mrs. Hardcastle by letting her \"suppose that I am in love with her son and she never once dreams that my affections are fixed upon another\". Hastings is the one Constance loves and not Tony. Tony, on his part, prefers Bet Bouncer to Constance. Because he is aware of his mother's plan to rob Constance of her inheritance, he agrees to be in love with his cousin, Constance, in the presence of his materialistic mother. </p><p>Constance Neville is in no way ready to part with her inheritance as she confides in Hastings, her lover. So she pleads with Hastings to bear with her until the moment the jewels are put into her hands; then, their marriage can take place. The more Constance persuades her aunt to allow her access to the jewels, even if for a day, the more Mrs. Hardcastle insists on her marrying Tony. Meanwhile, Hastings discovers that truly Tony prefers Bet Bouncer to Constance. He, therefore, persuades Tony to help steal the jewels from his mother. </p><p>Mrs. Hardcastle tells Tony to bear false witness before Constance, that the jewels are missing. Ironically, the jewels are indeed missing because Tony has given them to Hastings to enable him elope with Constance. Hastings immediately gives the jewels to Young Marlow for safe-keeping who, in turn, gives them to Mrs. Hardcastle for safe-keeping too. </p><p>Tony inform his mother that jewels are stolen. The mother then goes to check and discovers that the jewels are really missing. She raises an alarm that she's robbed but Marlow tells her that the jewels are with him and gives her the jewels.</p><p>The jewels help to accentuate the irony, comedy and indeed the mistakes of the night in advancing the plot. Through the jewels, Hasting and Constance's plan of elopement is exposed. The jewels bring out the selfish and materialistic character of Mrs. Hardcastle. </p><p> </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 8,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON - AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>SHE STOOPS TO CONQUER - OLIVER GOLDSMITH</strong></p><p> </p><p>Assess the role of Tony Lumpkin in the play.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Tony Lumpkin is the older child in the Hardcastle family. He is Mrs. Hardcastle's child by her first marriage. He is a spoilt child, thanks to his mother's permissive ways towards him. Obviously, Mr. Hardcastle would have been of help in bringing up Tony Lumpkin properly, but his wife will not allow it. He enjoys making practical jokes. </p><p>In the first place, Tony loves to spendhis time among the commoners in the village tavern. He is there when Young Marlow and Hastings come looking for their way to the Hardcastles. Tony takes this opportunity to pay his stepfather back for calling him names all the time. He misdirects the visitors, describing the Hardcastle home as an inn. This deception brings about exciting incidents in the plot. Young Marlow and Hastings go to the Hardcastles' house thinking it is an inn and the many mistakes of that night unfold, including the first meeting between Kate and Young Marlow. </p><p>Secondly, when Tony learns that Hastings means to elope with his cousin, Miss Neville, whom his mother has been busily courting for him, he is more than willing to steal her jewels for her to enable her elope with Hastings . Tony succeeds in this, and gives the jewels to Hastings who in turn gives them to Marlow for safekeeping. Mistakenly, Marlow hands over the jewels to Mrs. Hardcastle. As a result of this, Mrs. Hardcastle decides Miss Neville must go and live with Aunt Pedigree at Cracksku! Common. </p><p>Again, it is Tony Lumpkin who comes to the rescue of the lovers. He drives the carriage carrying his mother round and round pretending they are on the way to Aunt Pedigree. They end up close to where they set out from and later Hastings has to make a formal proposal to Miss Neville to settle matters. </p><p>To conclude, Tony Lumpkin seems to be the pivot around which the plot of the comedy develops. Any time he appears, a new event begins or a situation is saved.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 9,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION C: AFRICAN POETRY</strong></p><p> </p><p> </p><p>Examine the use of contrast in Okara's \"Piano and Drums'</p><p> </p>",
        "answer": "<p>The very title of the poem presents two contrasting musical instruments, a piano and drums. The former represents European culture while the latter, the African Culture. The poet uses these contrasting musical instruments to comment on their effects on him. The drums are simple and easy to play. On the other hand, the piano requires more effort to master. Auditorily, the drums are \"pulsing\" while the piano 'wails'. The drums invoke memories of a past gone by - a past of 'hunters crouched with spears', a simple life filled with dances. The piano, on the hand, speaks of complex ways. faraway lands and the poet bring lost in the labyrinth of its complexities.</p><p>At the symbolic level, contrast is used as a device to sharpen the differences between the cultures,and to convey the poet's attitude towards both. Interestingly, the poet devotes the first two stanzas to drums while only one stanza is assigned to the piano. This contrast in structure suggest his bias. It shows his sincere interest in the ways of his people. In each stanza, the poet examines the sound of the instrument and its effects on him. The piano is 'wailing' and speaks of \"faraway lands\" and complex ways, none of which the poet deciphers, leaving him confused.</p><p>The last stanza portrays the poet as one caught between the influence of two cultures. How ever, the force of the drums seems overwhelming and its tilts him towards the African culture.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 10,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION C: AFRICAN POETRY</strong></p><p> </p><p>Comment on the mood of the poet in \"Ambush\"</p>",
        "answer": "<p> \"Ambush\" portrays a society under siege. The isolation of the people pre-empts peace or prosperity. The powers that be appear to hold their subjects in a vice like grip.</p><p>By the use of powerful imagery and symbols, the metaphor of a voyage appropriately describes this poet unveils his mood despondency in his deprived transition. and gloomy circumstances. This is also the mood of the citizens of the land, who, individually and collectively, are denied any means or opportunities of improving their lot. By whatever means  imaginable (by sea, land or air), various agents, allies of \"the land\" (the autocracy) reinforce the deprivation of the people. The people's means of livelihood is obliterated; they are frightened and intimidated; their very existence is threatened. Above all, they dare not seek relief outside the land.</p><p>Through the metaphor of the \"giant whale\", the poet conveys the miserable picture of the people's chance of earning any livelihood being put paid to. The image of angling conveys this vividly, for the land swallows the angler's hook, line and sinker, thus aborting dreams of a good catch\".</p><p>Thus, the people are bereft of hope and expectation as their desires dwindle. The metaphor of the sea rves to convey the harsh restriction imposed on the people. The people are also held in terror unleashed by another agent of \"the land\" by land. The 'frightful tiger keeps the whole population in fear.  is exempted: both the old and the young dare not exhibit any bravado, nor venture out at night. This is how the \"land\" denies the people any escape by land. </p><p>The function of the agent that hovers overhead is to heighten the people's fear and invite chaos on them. The hawk continuously 'courts' ruin for the land with its \"hoots in space\". The impossibility of attempting to escape without being picked up is made certain by the hawk's presence. </p><p>Matters are sealed for the poor masses as local forces are harnessed and the \"land lies patiently ahead/awaiting in ambush\" for its own kith and kin. The purpose of the ambush is not to protect the people from invaders. Rather, it is to frustrate any attempt to escape for relief elsewhere. In the homeland, \"where nothing happens\", the signs of want are apparent and people need to migrate \"toward the shore of possibilities\". But they dare not.</p><p>The hopeless and frustrating circumstances of the poet make him utterly exasperated and depresed. Thus, the mood of hopelessness and frustration permeates the poem. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 11,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION D: NON-AFRICAN POETRY</strong></p><p> </p><p>How does the poet present death as a voyage in \"Crossing the Bar\"?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>In the poem, death is presented as the end of life on and the start of man's return to his maker. The metaphor of a voyage appropriately describes this transition. </p><p>The symbols marking the end of life are \"sunset and evening star\". These constitute \"one clear call for me\". Thus, the persona knows when his life has come to an end and he needs only to embark gladly on the voyage home. Death, therefore, is not to be feared. </p><p>The barrier between the mortal world and the world of eternity is the human body. This is represented by sand bar. At death, one's spirit leaves the mortal and is free to go \"home\". Without death, the spirit is not freed to set off. This makes death inevitable. <br>\nDeath is described as the final extinguishing of e light of life. It is when the light is gone that le sets out to board the eternity-bound vessel. his is captured succinctly as: </p><p>         \"Twilight and evening bell </p><p>          And after that the dark!\" </p><p>The symbols appropriately echo the earlier Isymbols, marking the end of life: </p><p>     \"Sunset and evening start</p><p>       And one clear call for me!\"</p><p>The certainty of death and the obvious final signposts are clearly put down in the poem. After death, the spirit is transported across the waves as it turns again home\". On crossing the bar, the spirit passenger boards the ship and must introduced to the Captain, that is, \"see my pilot face to face\".</p><p>The prospect of death and actually dying are not frightful, sorrowful or regrettable. They are all in the scheme of our mortality. As for the persona, he can take these in his stride. However, his experience has been that survivors do mourn for the dead. This is not necessary. He urges survivors of the dead thus: </p><p>\"And may there be no sadness of farewell When I embark.\" </p><p>His hope, which is almost a certainty, is that, when he has \"crost the bar\" (died), he will be quite safe meeting his \"Pilot\" who will take him to his destination, however far it is and however long the voyage lasts. </p><p>Through effective metaphors and imagery, death is presented as the inevitable close of the chapter of living on earth and the opening of the way \"again home\". </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 12,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION D: NON-AFRICAN POETRY</strong></p><p> </p><p>Examine Blake's use of diction in <em>The School Boy.</em></p>",
        "answer": "<p>`Diction' refers to the poet's choice of words and expressions and how he uses them to impact the theme.</p><p>Regarding theme, the poem deals with the restrictions imposed by the adults upon children's natural freedom, as these stifle their natural growth and development. Blake uses the natural rhythm of speech to convey this theme, particularly as he allows the boy to express himself in his own language, as much as possible. Apart from the rhymed stanzas, most of the lines read like colloquial speech. The following examples illustrate the point. In stanza one, the boy expresses his love of summer in the words: \"I love to rise in a summer morn\". Then in stanza two, he expresses his unhappiness about going to school in the line,\" Oh it drives all joy away\". Many more lines are couched in such monosyllabic words. </p><p>In addition to the above expressions, it can be said that the very words used in the poem are simple. Indeed, the longest word used in the entire poem is \"mellowing\" which is made up of three syllables. Words associated with spring and summer are used to describe the seasons positively. They include \"sing\", \"joy\" \"sweet company\", \"blossom\" and so on. The focus of the poem being summer, such words express the boy's delight in being associated with its activities. Similarly, in referring to spring time, he refers to \"bud\" and \"blossom\". However, words associated with school do not have positive associations. In school, the boy talks about \"sighing\" and \"dismay\" and \"dropping\". The teachers are \"a cruel eye outworn\" and school, which should be \"learning's bower\" has become a \"dreary shower\", The boy associates his misery with that of a \"bird caged\" and unable to \"sing\" or with that of a tender plant that has been \"stripped\" of its leaves, or with that of \"buds that have been nipped before they blossom\". </p><p>Indeed, there are many more negative words and expressions in the poem. These illustrate the boy's melancholic mood as he laments his inability to enjoy summer because of the insensitivity of his parents to his feelings and natural inclinations by sending him to school. However, beyond this meaning is one larger, which is the need to give children the opportunity to be self-expressive , so they can psychologically withstand the crisis of adulthood. It is to the poet's credit that such profound wisdom is conveyed in the simplicity of the vocabulary or diction. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 13,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E - African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>FACELESS - AMMA DARKO</strong></p><p> </p><p>Explain Kabira's presence in the hairdressing salon at Agbogboshie.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Agbogbloshie market is where Kabria shops for her vegetables. On the Monday following the discovery of Baby T's body behind a hairdressing salon, she and Fofo get acquainted under curious circumstances; disguised as a boy, the girl has attempted to steal Kabria's purse. </p><p>She is moved to rescue the 'boy' as a matter of conscience when 'he' is about to be lynched by the crowd that apprehend 'him', and 'he' restores Kabria's purse. </p><p>Earlier at the office of MUTE, the foursome officials — Dina, Vickie, Aggie and Kabria have discussed Fofo and Baby T and reached a consensus that Kabria ought to honour her appointment with Fofo at Agbogbloshie market to get to the bottom of the death of Baby T and Fofo's predicament. </p><p>All the above scenarios trigger Kabria's visit to the hairdressing salon. Kabria therefore goes to the salon at Agbogbloshie not to have her hair done, but to primarily conduct investigation to unravel the mystery surrounding the death of Baby T. Therefore, Kabria's presence in the hairdresser's salon is purely in her private capacity as an 'investigative reporter'. </p><p>Unfortunately for Kabria, her visit to the salon is initially a disappointment. She is unable to obtain information of any substance from the hairdresser. She is terse: 'To tell you the truth, my sister, what at all am I supposed to know?', and she shrugs. `Actually I didn't come to meet the body.\" Instead of information about the dead girl behind her salon, the hairdresser pours out her frustration about her broken marriage, which has saddled her with the responsibility to cater for the children of a runaway husband. Kabria wins her sympathy after telling her of a worse situation in her own marriage. She then directs her (Kabria) to see her senior apprentice for some details about the dead girl. </p><p>Kabria approaches the hairdresser's senior apprentice who makes interesting revelations: It appears Baby T is killed somewhere else and the body is dumped near the kiosk. The head of the Kayoyoos says Baby T is, not one of them. Three days after the corpse is dumped near the kiosk, pacification rites are performed at the spot by unknown persons. These, among others, leave more questions unanswered on Kabria's mind. </p><p>This, however, gingers Kabria and her colleagues into more actions. Eventually, Kabria's presence at the hairdresser's salon leads to a host of investigative activities that trace the murder of Baby T to the door step of Poison and Onko. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 14,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E - African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>FACELESS - AMMA DARKO</strong></p><p> </p><p>Comment on the significance of Sodom and Gomorrah in the Novel</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Sodom and Gomorrah is the seat of the various forms of evil in the world of Faceless. It is that part of the city where people can be said to be faceless and without an identity. It is home for hardened thieves, prostitutes and children driven from home or ones without a home. It is an area that is covered in filth and squalor. A the name implies, the place breeds all sorts of evil in the children who live there. Fofo, Odarley and the others do not leave home already depraved. It is the life at Sodom and Gomorrah that makes them so. </p><p>The goings-on in Sodom and Gomorrah are debasing. The best word to describe the morality of Sodom and Gomorrah is \"depraved\". The habits of the juvenile inhabitants who engage in acts of debauchery by \"drinking bottles of akpeteshie and watching adult films\" are deplorable. Youngsters steal and engage in prostitution for a living in the evil environment. Bullies like poison and Macho terrorise the children, deprive them of their money and even attempt to, and do rape the young helpless girls. There is no way of protecting these vulnerable young people. The early mention of Sodom and Gomorrah in the novel establishes its significance. It is a phenomenon that has \"catapulted from the pages of the Old testament to superimpose itself at Agbogbloshie\". </p><p>Sodom and Gomorrah is significant in a number of ways. When Kabria goes \"to visit Agbogbloshie Market for some garden eggs and tomatoes\", she meets a petty thief from Sodom and Gomorrah, who picks her purse. She saves the life of the pick-pocket who would have been subjected to instant mob justice (lynching). </p><p>Another aspect of Sodom and Gomorrah which is significant is its sustenance by those who profit from it. The coming of children into the streets and their living in Sodom and Gomorrah appear unstoppable. This is because of the activities of the likes of Maami Broni and Poison. Sodom and Gomorrah .depicts the hopelessness of the situation of children who are driven into the streets and have no prospects for the future. As the children are driven into the street, there are ready receivers who ensure that they stay, and they supervise their abuse. Sodom and Gomorrah is also significant in as far as no steps seem to be taken by the powers that be to intervene. Sodom and Gomorrah cries for cleansing but the state machinery does not hear or seem to care. The police are silent about, and invisible in, the affairs of the street children. No action is taken when crimes are reported to the police. </p><p>But for kabria's encounter with Fofo, the NGO MUTE would not have come to the rescue of the girl. The support of Harvest FM gives impetus to the MUTE effort. The questions, as to whether this single intervention of the non-governmental organisation is all there can be and whether it suffices, require critical answers. The enquires about the murdered girl found in the gutter receive lukewarm attention from the police. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 15,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E - African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>LONELY DAYS - BAYO ADEBOWALE</strong></p><p> </p><p>\"No woman's life is ever complete without a man\" How is this applicable to Yaremi in the Novel?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Yaremi, a beautiful widow in her early fifties in Kufi, has recently lost her husband, Ajumobi. Their children, all grown up including Alani, the only son, have left home. </p><p>Women I Kufi, by tradition, are only considered complete when they are part of a couple, even if they are the second or third wife. In the unfortunate event of the death of a husband, a woman is expected to re-marry. </p><p>Yaremi, being the strong-willed woman she is, decides against re-marriage to any of the available suitors. Nine months after the death of her husband, Yaremi is still without another husband, to the chagrin of the men in Kufi, who she tells she is \"neither a napkin nor a rag to clean up mess with\". Hence, she rejects all the caps of the three suitors who want to marry her. </p><p>With that firmly established, she then directs her energy towards filling the void left by Ajumobi's death. She decides to work hard, doing manual jobs to fill in the long hours of her lonely days under the hot sun. She does the farm work, cleans the family compound, dries maize grains, uproots cassava tubers for the goats, cooks, fetches water and firewood and does other household chores alongside her main job of buying and selling taffeta cloth in the market. Even so, there are certain jobs for which she requests assistance from the village men like Uncle Deyo. She still needs her husband to eat the food she prepares. She also needs, she realises, a husband to eliminate the termites, red ants and rats around the house. </p><p>Yaremi also longs for her husband's touch and his deep manly voice. in her loneliness, she dreams about him often and imagines he has come to visit her. She misses their quarrels and prays for him to return as it is impossible for her to forget certain events. </p><p>She tells Segi: \"Your father was to me like the mighty Baobab, King of Savannah, towering above ten thousand lesser trees around, protecting me under its cool shade... But death was cruel. It came like the harmattan blaze, to strip me of my only dress, my Baobab, leaving me to stand alone in mournful nakedness.\" </p><p>Thus, despite Yaremi's determination to stand against tradition in her refusal to re-marry, she realises that desirability of being part of a couple, as long as her husband is Ajumobi</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 16,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E - African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>LONELY DAYS - BAYO ADEBOWALE</strong></p><p> </p><p>Examine the author's narrative technique in the novel?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The author tells his story from the third person point of view. With this omniscient perspective, he demonstrates his skill in observing people and events very closely and passing appropriate comments on them. </p><p>One remarkable feature of the author's technique is his drawing very deeply very deeply from the African oral tradition in his narrative. This is evident in Yaremi's folk tales about such animals as the tortoise that often overreaches itself in its own wiles and cunning, the antelope that often falls on its own pride, and gluttonous baboon that dies from its rapacious greed. There is also the use of incantation as shown by both Ajumobi and Yaremi to neutralise the evil machinations of their perceived enemies. </p><p>The author employs flashback as Yaremi, on a good number of occasions, recalls the halcyon days with her late husband and eulogises his sterling qualities as a husband and his prowess as a hunter. </p><p>Another feature employed in the narration is dialogue. Instances are the exchanges between Yaremi and Woye, Yaremi and Ajumobi, Yaremi and her Suitors, the widows on their way from the river, etc. Indeed, the use of figurative language permeates the entire work. References can be made to the cap-picking ceremony where the suitors' personalities, etc., are delineated. <br>\n<br>\nAlso significant is the use of words or expressions drawn from the local language. Often, these put emphasis on tradition and folklore, thereby adding colour to the setting. There is also the use of traditional songs. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 17,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON - AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>NATIVE SON - RICHARD WRIGHT</strong></p><p> </p><p>Discuss the role of the black clergy in the Novel?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Rev. Hammond is a black clergyman of Bigger mother's church. Hence, he represents the black clergy and religion in the novel. </p><p>He visits Bigger in his cell. As soon as Bigger recognizes him, he is on guard against him. Bigger fears the pastor will make him feel remorseful and wants to tell him to go but cannot speak. </p><p>Reverend Hammond kneels on the concrete floor to pray for the salvation of Bigger's soul. He repeatedly refers to Bigger as 'poor boy', seeing Bigger as a sinner who needs salvation. As the words of the pastor's prayer register themselves in Bigger's consciousness, they make him remember his mother's voice telling of suffering, hope and love beyond the world. This makes Bigger feel condemned and guilty. </p><p>Bigger hates the clergyman's creed and wishes he will stop praying. He cannot repeat any of the preacher's words, but they make him (Bigger) feel like leaping up to strike him. Before he leaves. Reverend Hammond gives Bigger a wooden cross. trying to make him believe that life is all suffering. This, Bigger rejects in his heart. </p><p>The visit and the prayer of the black clergyrnz.,. expose the hypocritical attitude of the black churc and its attitude of capitulating to the situation of i members. It is ironical that the church cannot eve engage the services of a lawyer for Bigger, which what he needs at this time. This, Reveren Hammond knows as he tells Jan that if anybody needs help, then Bigger does. </p><p>The clergy contrasts Jan, not only in race ar occupation, but in his belief in what man needs life. Jan forgives Bigger and engages a lawyer to defend him now. But Reverend Hammond thinks of the hereafter. Bigger's case needs prompt and immediate attention, but the clergyman offers freedom of the soul, whilst Jan offers immediate and prompt attention. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 18,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON - AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>NATIVE SON - RICHARD WRIGHT</strong></p><p>What have you learned about black life from the conversation between Bigger and Gus at the entrance of the pool room?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Bigger leaves home that fateful morning to avoid his mother's incessant nagging about the family's poor living condition and his not able to be of any help. She warns him against his continued involvement with the gang and prophesies doom for him if he disregards her warning. He heads for the pool room where he feels more at ease. He meets Gus, a member of the gang at the entrance and they drift into a conversation. </p><p>Their conversation reveals much about the living conditions of the black people. It exposes their forced segregated lives, theft exclusion from participation in the political, military and commercial life of white America, as well as their bottled up frustration which stir up anger in some of them. </p><p>We learn, for instance, that blacks live under very poor conditions. As Bigger and Gus observe and 3 appreciate nature, i.e., the warm day, both reflect on the poor heating system in their homes. Though their landlords 'don't give much heat, they always demand r rent. They reflect also on their segregated lives, which bother them a lot. Bigger observes that whites live \"over across the line, over there on Cottage Grove Avenue\". Explaining the source of their bitterness, e he intones: \"We live here, and they live there, we black and they white. They get things and we ain't. They do things and we can't.\" Accounting for his feeling, he says. \" I feel like I'm on the outside of the world peeping in through a knot-hole in the fence</p><p>Bigger and Gus refer also to the power structure in American society, from the presidency to the military, business and commerce. Their simulation of a telephone conversation between the president of the United States and his secretary of state on the one hand, and J.P. Morgan, a business mogul and someone else is also revealing. It is revealed that the president's secretary of state is more ready to attend a cabinet meeting about \" the niggers raising sand all over the country\" than one involving Germans. And J.P. Morgan is prepared to \"sell twenty thousand shares of US steel, a mind-boggling figure. That kinds of business transaction is way beyond blacks to do. These show the extent to which whites suppress to put blacks in their place. </p><p>Blacks are also prevented from aspiring to do anything worthwhile, \"They get the chance to do everything\", but \" they don't let us do anything.\" Whereas the whites, like the pigeon, can go wherever they want, the blacks are restricted in their movements. </p><p>The conversation reveals two contrasting attitude of the blacks towards their situation in the novel. Some blacks, like Gus, are resigned to their fate. Others, like Bigger, breed anger in themselves against the system. </p><p>Thus, the conversation gives a microscopic view of black life in the novel. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 19,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON-AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>THE CASTLE OF OTRANTO - HORACE WALPOLE</strong></p><p> </p><p>Comment on the significance of Conrad's death in the novel?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Conrad's death is significant both in its contribution to plot development and also to character delineation. </p><p>Conrad, son and heir of Manfred, dies when he is mysteriously crushed by a gigantic stone helmet. He does not really appear as a character in the novel but is very important and his death has a direct influence on the major actions in the novel. </p><p>Conrad is supposed to marry Isabella, daughter of Frederic. Frederic is, in actual fact, the real heir to the Castle of Otranto. Manfred arranges the marriage between Conrad and Isabella in order to unite the two factions claiming rights to Otranto. Conrad's death puts paid to Manfred's attempt to consolidate his own position through his son. Thus, he turns his attention to other means to attain his goal. This sets into motion a chain of events which culminate in his downfall and the restoration of the Castle of Otranto to Theodore who is declared as the true heir of the castle. The prophecy that the castle will be restored to its rightful heir \"whenever the owner should be grown too large to inhabit it\" is thus fulfilled. </p><p>Isabella's repugnance at the idea of her marrying Manfred, after his proposed divorce of his wife, Hippolita, leads her to run away from the castle to the church of St. Nicholas, to seek the protection of Friar Jerome. This action is in itself significant since it brings the holy father into direct conflict with Manfred. This advances the plot as it creates the occasion for the Manfred to sin further by challenging the spiritual powers. </p><p>Conrad's death also introduces Theodore into the action of the novel. Theodore's explanation on discovery of the dead Conrad generates a conflict between him and Manfred. Theodore's affiance with Isabella complicates the novel's plot further. Manfred mistakenly believes that the two are in love much to his annoyance as he regards it as an affront to his authority. The stage is therefore set for the final confrontation in the novel which results in Manfred's downfall and the return of the Castle of Otranto to its rightful heir. </p><p>Conrad's death also contributes to the delineation of Manfred's character. It exposes Manfred's depravity and his capacity for evil machinations. Conrad's death leaves him with only one option as he sees it to consolidate his hold on the castle. When his attempt to obtain Isabella's consent to marry him by manipulation and subterfuge fails, he resorts to violence. His lechery and unscrupulousness are accentuated by Conrad's removal from the scene, and he is exposed for what he really is. With the introduction of Theodore immediately after Conrad's death, a formidable opponent to Manfred's evil plans emerges. </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 20,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON-AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>THE CASTLE OF OTRANTO - HORACE WALPOLE</strong></p><p> </p><p>Examine the relationship between Manfred and Hippolita</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Manfred, the Prince of Otranto, is married to Hippolita, a lady he later points out to be a distant relation of his. </p><p>They have two children, Matilda, their eighteen-year-old daughter and Conrad, their fifteen-year-old son. </p><p>Hippolita is described as \"an amiable lady\" and is presented in the novel as a subservient wife who treats her husband with utmost respect. Her love for and dedication to her husband is not reciprocated. This is so because Manfred's attitude towards her is one of utter disdain, though he himself says of her, \"true, I honour Hippolita's virtue, I think her a saint...\". </p><p>In the first place, he does not take her suggestions into consideration. When Manfred hatches the plot for the marriage between Conrad and Isabella, Hippolita calls his attention to the fact that Conrad, their ailing son, is too young to marry. Manfred responds by blaming her inability to give him more than one heir. The marriage plan ends disastrously with the mysterious death of Conrad on the wedding day. </p><p>Manfred's inhumane treatment of his wife only intensifies after Conrad's death. Hippolita, on <br>\nrecovering from the initial shock at the news, demands regular updates on her \"lord\" — the way she refers to Manfred. Manfred, on the other hand, does not even mention his wife or daughter, as the first words he utters to the ladies in the chapel after the incident are: \"Take care of the Lady Isabella\". Hippolita sends Matilda, their daughter to see how Manfred is coping with his loss. When Matilda attempts to do so, she cannot find words to explain to her mother the 'bitter' reception she has received from her father, on her return to Hippolita. </p><p>Hippolita, on her part, registers her disappointment that Manfred has not requested to see her when she says mournfully: \"But will he not let me see him? Will he not permit me to blend my tears with his, and shed a mother's sorrow in the bossom of her lord?\" <br>\nShe is also worried that Conrad's tragic death must have affected Manfred very badly and demands that she be taken to see him, when she says to her maids: \"Raise me, my maidens; I will see my lord. Bear me to him instantly: He is dearer to me than my children.\" </p><p>It is heart-rending that Manfred does not care or ask to see his wife but sends to summon Isabella instead. Hippolita, in her innocence, thinks that Manfred is apprehensive of meeting herself and Matilda and that, that is why he chooses to send for Isabella instead. She tells Isabella, \"Console him. dear Isabella and tell him I will smother my own anguish rather than add to his\". </p><p>This is contrary to an ideal marriage relationship situation where, at least, both the husband and wife show concern for each other. Little does Hippolita know that Manfred is desirous to propose to Isabella. She trusts her husband very much. </p><p>When Isabella, on hearing the proposal, flees the castle, Manfred is in hot pursuit of her. Recognising Manfred's footsteps on the stairs, Hippolita hastily goes out anxious to meet him for the first time after son's death. He pushes her \"rudely off' demanding to know Isabella's whereabouts and even mentions Hippolita is jealous of Isabella. Hippolita, though surprised at this utterance, being the obedient wife she is, carries out Manfred's orders to send he-chaplain to him. Hippolita later tells Manfred that the 'gigantic leg' is just a figment of the imagination Manfred is relieved but his attitude towards his does not improve; in fact, it gets worse. </p><p>It is evident that the relationship between Manfred and his wife is strange and appears to be unhappy one for hippolita.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 21,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E - African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>AMMA DARKO - FACELESS</strong></p><p> </p><p>Show how women are discriminated against in the novel.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates are expected to mention the following point, among others:</p><p>i. Women generally left with the task of raising children single-handedly e.g Maa Tsuru.</p><p>ii. Men being uninterested in the welfare of women.</p><p>iii. Women being treated like sex objects - people without feelings.</p><p>iv. Women being treated violently.</p><p>v. Men not being punished for their escapades.</p><p> </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 22,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E: African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>AMMA DARKO: Faceless</strong></p><p> </p><p>Assess the role of MUTE in the novel.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points are expected from the candidates.</p><p>i. The setting up of MUTE and its mission.</p><p>ii. Kabria's scoop which leads MUTE to investigate the plight of street children like Fofo and Baby T.</p><p>iii. The exposure of the reluctance of the law enforcers to investigate street crime.</p><p>iv. The combined efforts of MUTE and Harvest FM which unearth street crime and its perpetrators and prick public conscience.</p><p>v. The discovery of atrocities of children against children.</p><p>vi. The fight against crime and immorality in the society. <br>\n<br>\n </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 23,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E - African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>BAYO ADEBOWALE: Lonely Days</strong></p><p> </p><p>What impression do you form of Yaremi in the novel?</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points should be well developed by the candidates:</p><p>i. Yaremi is the central character in the novel.</p><p>ii.  Yaremi exudes strength and quality which can be admired.</p><p>iii. Yaremi as industrious and also a dedicated and dutiful housewife.</p><p>iv. Yaremi is generous and also independent.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 24,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E - African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>BAYO ADEBOWALE: Lonely Days</strong></p><p> </p><p>How does Ajumobi’s death contribute to the development of the plot?</p><p></p>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. Ajumobi’s death brings to the fore the plight of Yaremi and other widows.</p><p>ii. It sets the chain of Yaremi’s suffering as a widow in motion, e.g. her loneliness, ostracism.</p><p>iii. It unearths some of the superstitions and cultural practices of the society.</p><p>iv. It engenders flashback in Yaremi which underscores her love for her late husband.</p><p>v. His death does not kill his memory. He is used as a measure to assess other men, e.g. the three suitors at the cap-picking ceremony.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 25,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON - AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>RICHARD WRIGHT: Native Son</strong></p><p> </p><p>How does fear influence Bigger Thomas’ actions in the novel?</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points are expected from the candidates:</p><p>i. Bigger’s fear of the rat and his killing of it.</p><p>ii. Bigger’s background in a black segregated south side of Chicago.</p><p>iii. Bigger’s frustrated dream of flying.</p><p>iv. The aborted robbery.</p><p>v. His experience of the white world in the Dalton’s home and his smothering of Mary to death, all driven by his fear of failure.</p><p>vi. His decapitation and burning of Mary’s body.</p><p>vii. His murder of Bessie Mears.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 26,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON - AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>RICHARD WRIGHT: Native Son</strong></p><p> </p><p>With reference to three symbols, discuss Wright’s use of symbolism in the novel.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates are expected to mention the following points:</p><p>i. The rat as a symbol of poverty, dirt, helplessness etc.</p><p>ii. The rat parallels Bigger as a symbol of the oppressed.</p><p>iii. Mrs Dalton’s blindness as the symbol of the internal blindness of the white racists.</p><p>iv. The colour symbols to signify blood, snow and skin.</p><p>v. The snow falling to symbolize the stifling white society.</p><p>vi. The flying plane symbolizing the failed aspirations of the black boy.</p><p>vii. The cross as a symbol of salvation and damnation.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 27,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON-AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>HORACE WALPOLE: The Castle of Otranto </strong></p><p> </p><p>Examine the importance of Frair Jerome in the development of the plot.</p><p></p>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates are expected to mention the following points among others:</p><p>i. Friar Jerome and his priestly duties.</p><p>ii. His interaction with the persons in the castle – Hippolita, Matilda, Isabella and Manfred.</p><p>iii. His role in quelling turbulence in the castle.</p><p>iv. Frair as the biological father of Theodore.</p><p>v. His upholding of the prophecy about the principality of Otranto.</p><p>vi. He witnesses the marriage of Isabella and Theodore.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 28,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON-AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>HORACE WALPOLE: The Castle of Otranto</strong></p><p> </p><p>Comment on Manfred’s greed for power in the novel.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points are expected from the candidates:</p><p>i. Manfred’s usurpation of the Castle of Otranto.</p><p>ii. Manfred’s scheming to hold on to the castle in perpetuity through marriage ties.</p><p>iii. His ill-treatment of Theodore whom he sees as a threat.</p><p>iv. Manfred’s defiance of the prophecy and continuing scheme.</p><p>v. The fulfilment of the prophecy leading to the loss of his children and the castle.</p><p> </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 29,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION A: African Drama</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>DELE CHARLEY: The Blood of a Stranger</strong></p><p> </p><p>Discuss the contribution of Parker to the development of the play.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>I. Parker, a black man and spokesman of Whitehead, who advances the plot.</p><p>II. Kindo’s treatment of Parker and the white man.</p><p>III. Parker’s report of Wara’s escape from Whitehead.</p><p>IV. Whitehead’s intention to dispense with Parker and his assignment to his spokesman.</p><p>V. The consequence of Parker’s killing of Soko.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 30,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION A: African Drama</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>DELE CHARLEY: The Blood of a Stranger</strong></p><p> </p><p>Consider the view that tradition triumphs in the play.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. The people’s adherence to custom or tradition.</p><p>ii. The three stalwarts of the people’s culture or tradition and their differences/rivalry.</p><p>iii. The effect of the conflict among the three characters: Kindo, Soko and Maligu.</p><p>iv. Whitehead’s mission and its failure.</p><p>v. The triumph of custom or traditions in the killings in the shrine and Kindo’s banishment.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 31,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section A: AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>FRANK OGODO OGBECHE - Harvest of Corruption</strong></p><p> </p><p>How does Chief Haladu Ade-Amaka manipulate justice to his advantage?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates are expected to discuss the following points:</p><p>i. The theme of bribery and corruption as tools of the manipulation.</p><p>ii. Chief Haladu Ade-Amaka as the kingpin of corruption.</p><p>iii. Other corrupt individuals/corrupt officers of the law and their influence.</p><p>iv. Failure of the vigilance of corruption.</p><p>v. Eventual triumph of justice.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 32,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section A: AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>FRANK OGODO OGBECHE - Harvest of Corruption</strong></p><p> </p><p>Examine the portrayal of Ochuole in the play.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. Ochuole as an immoral person and agent of corruption.</p><p>ii. Her job and relationship with Chief Ade-Amaka.</p><p>iii. Her deceptive nature and insincerity to Aloho.</p><p>iv. Her modus operandi and association with Madam Hoha.</p><p>v. Her just eventual punishment.</p><p> </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 33,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>LORRAINE HANSBERRY - A Raisin In The Sun</strong></p><p> </p><p>To what extent are the dreams of the Younger family fulfilled in the play?</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates are expected to discuss the following points:</p><p>i. Each member of the Younger family and his or her dream.</p><p>ii. Mama’s dream and Ruth’s dream.</p><p>iii. Beneatha’s dream and Walter’s dream.</p><p>iv. How much of each dream is fulfilled.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 34,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>LORRAINE HANSBERRY - A Raisin In The Sun</strong></p><p> </p><p>Discuss the living conditions of the Younger family.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates are expected to discuss:</p><p>i. The composition of the Younger family.</p><p>ii. The matriarchal role of Mama.</p><p>iii. The general living conditions of the family.</p><p>iv. The effect of these conditions on the expectations of members of the family.</p><p>v. The collective desire for change.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 35,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON - AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>OLIVER GOLDSMITH - SHE STOOPS TO CONQUER</strong></p><p> </p><p>What makes Mr. Hardcastle a humorous character?</p><p> </p>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. Mr Hardcastle as the owner of an old country mansion and his love of the countryside and old things.</p><p>ii. His sense of humour and teasing of/his relationship with his wife.</p><p>iii. His tolerance of his treatment by Tony Lumpkin, Young Marlow and Hastings.</p><p>iv. Qualities that qualify him as humorous.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 36,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON - AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>OLIVER GOLDSMITH - SHE STOOPS TO CONQUER</strong></p><p> </p><p>Discuss the significance of the alehouse in the play.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates were expected to discuss the following points:</p><p>i. Identification of the alehouse.</p><p>ii. The patrons of alehouse and its importance to Tony Lumpkin.</p><p>iii. Revelations about Tony in the alehouse.</p><p>iv. Opportunity for meeting Marlow and Hastings first and deceiving them.</p><p>v. Contribution to the theme of the play.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 37,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Comment on the poet’s use of imagery in The Dining Table<em>.</em></p><p> </p><p></p>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points are expected from the candidates:</p><p>i. Imagery of the effects of war.</p><p>ii. Pain, suffering and famine.</p><p>iii. Violence and terror.</p><p>iv. Fear and insecurity.</p><p>v. Sickness and disease.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 38,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Consider the theme of culture neglect in Diop’s Vanity</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. Effects of civilisation on African cultural values.</p><p>ii. The poet’s unhappiness with the prevailing situation which he considers ridiculous and demeaning.</p><p>iii. The poet’s use of words/phrases to call attention to the neglect of ancestral counselling and guidance.</p><p>iv. His certainty that only ancestral guidance and counselling can solve their problem.</p><p>v. The profitability of sticking to African culture.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 39,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Comment on Birches as a descriptive poem</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The following are expected from the candidates:</p><p>i. The poem as a descriptive poem.</p><p>ii. The agents of birch bending: nature and the country boy.</p><p>iii. The sun’s warm light and its effect on the icy weight on the birch.</p><p>iv. The comparison of the drooping leaves of the birch to the hanging hair of crawling girls.</p><p>v. The poet’s wish to leave the earth awhile by swinging a birch and return to earth.</p><p> </p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 40,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Examine the relationship between God and man in The Pulley.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answer should include the following points:</p><p>i. God’s endowment to man and creation.</p><p>ii. The withholding of rest from man.</p><p>iii. Justification for God’s withholding rest from man.</p><p>iv. The effect of withholding rest from man.</p><p>v. How man’s restlessness serves God’s purpose.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 41,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E: African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>AMMA DARKO: Faceless</strong></p><p> </p><p>Examine the role and significance of Sylv Po in the novel.</p>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points are expected from the candidates:</p><p>i. Sylv Po as an investigative journalist.</p><p>ii. His intervention with NGOs in solving problems relating to street children.</p><p>iii. Examples of his intervention.</p><p>iv. Criminal’s attempt to escape justice by listening in and contributing to Sylv Po’s talk show.</p><p>v. Sylv Po’s action exposing the incompetence of the police.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 42,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E: African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>AMMA DARKO: Faceless</strong></p><p> </p><p>Comment on Kabria’s challenges in the novel.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points are expected from the candidates:</p><p>i. Kabria’s occupation (background).</p><p>ii. Her work at MUTE.</p><p>iii. Her involvement in Fofo and Baby T’s case.</p><p>iv. Adade and the children/involvement.</p><p>v. Creamy and her continual breakdowns.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 43,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<h3> </h3><p><strong>SECTION E - African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>BAYO ADEBOWALE: Lonely Days</strong></p><p> </p><p>Examine the attitude of the people of Kufi towards death in the novel.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. The people’s attitude to death based on their cultural beliefs.</p><p>ii. Categories of death in Kufi: good and bad.</p><p>iii. Suspicion surrounding death.</p><p>iv. Death as a transition from the physical to the spiritual.</p><p>v. The dead offer a helping hand.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 44,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION E - African Prose</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>BAYO ADEBOWALE: Lonely Days</strong></p><p> </p><p>Discuss Ajumobi as a man and husband in the novel.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points should be well developed by the candidates:</p><p>i. Our posthumous encounter with Ajumobi.</p><p>ii. His stature and occupation.</p><p>iii. Ajumobi as a sociable man.</p><p>iv. Ajumobi as a traditionalist.</p><p>v. Ajumobi as a polygamist.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 45,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON - AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>RICHARD WRIGHT: Native Son</strong></p><p> </p><p>How does the media respond to the disappearance of Mary Dalton in the novel?</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. The anxiety of the media for information about the disappearance of Mary Dalton.</p><p>ii. Bigger becoming apprehensive because of the invasion of the media.</p><p>iii. The media responses leading to Bigger’s flight.</p><p>iv. Media response showing racism.</p><p>v. Media response predetermining the trial.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 46,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON - AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>RICHARD WRIGHT: Native Son</strong></p><h3> </h3><p>What are Bigger’s reasons for his bitterness against the white man in the novel?</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points should be well developed by the candidates:</p><p>i. Bigger’s bitterness as a reaction to the oppressive system of segregation.</p><p>ii. Bigger’s bitterness as a reaction to the lack of opportunities.</p><p>iii. Bigger’s bitterness resulting from the feeling that his relationship with others, as well as with the blacks, is conditioned.</p><p>iv. Bigger’s bitterness as a result of blacks’ exclusion from politics.</p><p>v. Bigger’s bitterness as a result of the sense of shame instilled by racial segregation.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 47,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON-AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>THE CASTLE OF OTRANTO - HORACE WALPOLE</strong></p><h3> </h3><p>What does Theodore’s encounter with Isabella in the cavern in the forest reveal about his character?</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates are expected to mention the following points:</p><p>i. Theodore is the son of Father Jerome (the Priest at St. Nicholas)</p><p>ii. Theodore as a good-natured character.</p><p>iii. Theodore as a gallant/chivalrous chacter.</p><p>iv. Theodore’s faithfulness to his lover.</p><p>v. Theodore as a truthful/selfless/disciplined character.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 48,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION F: NON-AFRICAN PROSE</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>THE CASTLE OF OTRANTO - HORACE WALPOLE</strong></p><p> </p><p>Comment on the issue of male dominance in the novel.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points are expected from the candidates:</p><p>i. Male characters’ control of the political life of the novel.</p><p>ii. Male dominance over women’s choice of partners.</p><p>iii. Presentation of women as inferior to men.</p><p>iv. Denial of women’s right to inheritance (culturally).</p><p>v. Male dominance of religious code.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 49,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION A: African Drama</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>DELE CHARLEY: The Blood of a Stranger</strong></p><p> </p><p>Consider the view that Whitehead is not to blame for the troubles of Mando land.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points are expected from the candidates:</p><p>i. The custom of Mando land compromised.</p><p>ii. Whitehead’s role.</p><p>iii. Maligu’s role.</p><p>iv. Soko’s role.</p><p>v. Santigi’s role.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 50,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION A: African Drama</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>DELE CHARLEY: The Blood of a Stranger</strong></p><p> </p><p>Comment on Wara as an admirable character.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. Wara is identified as Kindo’s woman.</p><p>ii. She is the voice of reason for Kindo, and will not take liberties with tradition.</p><p>iii. She is submissive but also courageous.</p><p>iv. She is Kindo’s trusted friend and partner.</p><p>v. She is supportive, protective and confident.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 51,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section A: AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>FRANK OGODO OGBECHE - Harvest of Corruption</strong></p><p> </p><p>Examine the role of religion in the play.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. An explanation of religion.</p><p>ii. Characters that manifest religious attitudes.</p><p>iii. Instances where religious influences are shown.</p><p>iv. The consequence of being steadfast in one’s religious belief.</p><p>v. The fate of the corrupt and irreligious characters</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 52,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section A: AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>FRANK OGODO OGBECHE - Harvest of Corruption</strong></p><p> </p><p>Discuss the major female characters in the play.</p><p> </p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The following points are expected from the candidates:</p><p>i. Identification of the major female characters.</p><p>ii. Aloho, her predicament and how she falls victim to Ochuole and Chief.</p><p>iii. Ochuole and the role she plays.</p><p>iv. Madam Hoha, her contribution to the corruption ring and the penalty she faces.</p><p>v. Ogeyi and what she stands for.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 53,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>LORRAINE HANSBERRY - A Raisin In The Sun</strong></p><p> </p><p>Compare George Murchison’s and Karl Linder’s attitudes to the Younger family.</p><p> </p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. The intermingling of race and class complicating issues as represented by George Murchison and Karl Lindner – one black, one white.</p><p>ii. George’s disdain for his African heritage on seeing Beneatha in African costume and his snobbish attitude towards Walter’s attempt to fraternise with him.</p><p>iii. George’s show of knowledge about western civilization and social class.</p><p>iv. Lindner being a white racist demanding that the Youngers consider not moving into their apartment at Clybourne Park.</p><p>v. Lindner’s insensitivity to the plight of the Youngers and Murchison’s condescending disregard of the Youngers’ sensibility, which link the two as racist.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 54,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>LORRAINE HANSBERRY - A Raisin In The Sun</strong></p><p> </p><p>Comment on the relationship between Walter and Ruth Younger in the play.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates should include these in their answers:</p><p>i. Identifying/Establishing the relationship between Ruth and Walter.</p><p>ii. The effect of their living condition on their relationship.</p><p>iii. The strains and joys in their relationship.</p><p>iv. Their attempt to love, as Ruth tries to do her duty towards her family while Walter plays the blame game.</p><p>v. Both eventually realising the need to improve their marital relationship.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 55,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON - AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>SHE STOOPS TO CONQUER - OLIVER GOLDSMITH</strong></p><p> </p><p>Discuss the significance of night to the play.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. Night not only aspect of time or setting.</p><p>ii. Significance in the Marlow/Kate relationship.</p><p>iii. Significance of night in the ensuring attempt to transfer Constance to Aunt Pedigree.</p><p>iv. Night engendering the other title of the play.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 56,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>Section B: NON - AFRICAN DRAMA</strong></p><p> </p><p><strong>OLIVER GOLDSMITH - SHE STOOPS TO CONQUER</strong></p><p> </p><p>How do Young Marlow and Hastings view Tony Lumpkin in the play?</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates are expected to discuss the following points:</p><p>i. The journey of young Marlow and George Hastings to the Hardcastles’</p><p>ii. The preconceived notion of Tony Lumpkin as a spoilt child.</p><p>iii. Hastings’ modified perception of Tony who hatches a plan for Hastings and Constance to elope.</p><p>iv. Hastings’ perception of Tony as a traitor and loss of confidence in Tony.</p><p>v. Young Marlow’s unchanging perception of Tony as a spoilt child, though Hastings’ opinion changes.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 57,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Discuss the theme of oppression in “The Dining Table”.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates are expected to discuss the following points:</p><p>i. The fact that this is a protest poem.</p><p>ii. Details of the dining table and the bizarre menu.</p><p>iii. The widespread suffering in the community.</p><p>iv. The poet’s resolve to lead a revolution.</p><p>v. The impression that the oppression will not end, which reinforces the theme.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 58,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Examine the use of repetition and rhetorical question in Diop’s “Vanity”.</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answers should include:</p><p>i. Statement/Explanation of the theme.</p><p>ii. Relevance of the use of the devices.</p><p>iii. Identification of repetition and its literary function in explaining/advancing the theme.</p><p>iv. Identification of rhetorical question and its literary function in explaining/advancing the theme.</p><p>v. The combined effects of these in accentuating the frustrations of the living.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 59,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p><strong>SECTION D: NON-AFRICAN POETRY</strong></p><p> </p><p>Comment on the theme of uncertainty in “Crossing the Bar”</p><ol>\n</ol><p> </p>",
        "answer": "<p>Candidates are expected to discuss the following points:</p><p>i. The theme of death as a transition.</p><p>ii. The certainty of death and the persona’s hope for life hereafter.</p><p>iii. Crossing the bar and its attendant strains.</p><p>iv. The sorrows of those left behind.</p><p>v. The hope of meeting his creator eventually.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    },
    {
        "course": "literature",
        "institution": "waec",
        "order": 60,
        "year": 2018,
        "question": "<p>Discuss the use of any three images in Frost’s “Birches”</p><ol>\n</ol>",
        "answer": "<p>The required answer should include the following points:</p><p>i. The explanation of the term, “image” and its relevance to the theme.</p><p>ii. The theme of the poem.</p><p>iii. The use of sight images.</p><p>iv. The use of sound images.</p><p>v. The use of images associated with heat and cold.</p><p>vi. The use of tactile images.</p><p>vii. Combination of these in anchoring the theme.</p>",
        "type": "theory"
    }
]